<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R4/fhir-single.xsd">
  <a name="capability"> </a>
  <h3>Capabilities</h3>
  <p>
    While implementers are free to pick and choose useful functionality from this IG as they see fit, in order to claim conformance with this IG, a system must
    declare that it implements one or more of the four <a href="workflow.html#actors">capability statements</a> described on the <a href="workflow.html">Workflow</a> page.
    I.e. All systems that conform with this specification must, at minimum, satisfy the <b>SHALL</b> requirements listed in at least one of the following CapabilityStatement 
    instances:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-care-manager.html">Care Manager</a>,</li>
    <li><a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-patient-engagement.html">Patient Engagement App</a>,</li>
    <li><a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-service-provider-full.html">Full Service Provider</a>, and/or</li>
    <li><a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-service-provider-light.html">Light Service Provider</a></li>
  </ul>
  
  <a name="conventions"> </a>
  <h3>Conventions</h3>
  <p>
    This implementation guide documents conformance expectations through declarations in computable artifacts, such as cardinality and vocabulary bindings in 
    IG <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}profiling.html">profiles</a>.  However, it also makes use of conformance language in the text of the IG.  When expressed in upper-case,
    the words <b>SHALL</b>, <b>SHOULD</b>, <b>MAY</b>, etc. are to be interpreted as described in the FHIR core specification 
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}conformance-rules.html#conflang">here</a>.
  </p>

  <a name="mustSupport"> </a>
  <h4>Must Support</h4>
	<p>
    FHIR defines the notion of <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}conformance-rules.html#mustSupport">Must Support</a> to help establish conformance expectations for systems.  
    The specific meaning of "must support" is left to be defined in individual implementation guides.  For the purposes of <i>this</i> implementation guide, "must support" 
    shall be interpreted as follows:
  </p>
  <img style="float:right;padding:3px" src="workout.png" alt="A Woman in Brown Leggings Holding a Dumbbell"/>
	<ul>
		<li>Data Sources <b>SHALL</b> be capable of populating the data element when sharing resources compliant with the profile. I.e. the system must be able 
      to demonstrate the population and sharing of the element, but it is acceptable to omit the element if the system does not have values in a particular 
      instance. A system that is incapable of ever sharing the element would be non-conformant.</li>
    <li>Data Consumers <b>SHALL</b> be capable of processing resource instances containing the data elements and doing something useful with them - i.e. displaying,
      storing, or any other action a reasonable user would expect the system to take with a 'supported' element of that type.</li>
    <li>If the minimum cardinality of an element is greater than 0 – i.e. the element is ‘required’, then the element <b>SHALL</b> be present in the instance and 
      <b>SHALL</b> have a value unless:
      <ul>
        <li>The profile explicitly declares the <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}extension-data-absent-reason.html">data-absent-reason</a> extension or other 
          extension for the element, in which case an extension can be present in place of the value.</li>
        <li>The profile is inherited from U.S. Core, in which case a data-absent-reason extension may be sent in place of the value even where data-absent-reason is not explicitly 
          declared in the profile.</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Data Consumers <b>SHALL</b> interpret missing data elements within resource instances as data not being present in the Data Source's systems or was not deemed to be 
      shareable with the Data Consumer for privacy or other business reasons.</li>
    <li>Where the value set for an element includes concepts such as "unknown", "refused to answer", "not available" or where data-absent-reason is explicitly referenced in a 
      profile, then Data Sources <b>SHALL</b> use these values/that extension to communicate the reason for missing data.</li>
    <li>Data Consumers <b>SHALL</b> be able to process resource instances containing data elements that have extensions in place of a value where such extensions are declared as 
      part of the profile.</li>
	</ul>
	<p>NOTE: These expectations are largely drawn from those defined in the <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/davinci-hrex/STU1/conformance.html">Da Vinci Health Record Exchange
	  (HRex)</a> IG.</p>
	
	<a name="profiles"> </a>
	<h4>Handling profiles and modifiers</h4>
	<p>
	  This IG makes significant use of <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}profiling.html">profiles</a> to describe both the expected content of instances, as well as which
	  data elements systems are expected to <a href="#mustSupport">support</a>.  However, not all data hosted by a system will necessarily comply with one of the profiles
	  defined in this IG.  Data consumers <b>SHALL</b> tolerate receipt of data in response to queries that do not comply with profiles defined in this IG, though they
	  <b>MAY</b> opt to ignore data that does not conform to the profiles or choose to process it.  All resources that declare a
	  <a href="CodeSystem-pa-temporary-codes.html#pa-temporary-codes-PhysicalActivity">Physical Activity</a> category <b>SHOULD</b> conform with their respective profile(s)
	  in this IG.
	</p>
	<p>
	  In addition to potentially receiving non-conformant data, conformant instances <b>MAY</b> contain additional data elements not marked in these profiles as 'mustSupport.  
	  So long as the elements found are valid in the base <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}">FHIR R4</a> resource definitions, systems <b>SHALL</b> accept such instances unless 
	  the elements present are <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}elementdefinition-definitions.html#ElementDefinition.isModifier">modifier elements</a>.  Non-modifier elements 
	  <b>MAY</b> be ignored.  Modifier elements will generally cause the instances to be non-conformant with the profiles of this IG and may be either ignored or subject to
	  special processing that takes into account the fact that the meaning of the instances may differ from what is typically expected.
	</p>
	<p>
	  If a system has data with modifier elements that are prohibited by this specification, it is free to send such data.  However, these resources will not comply with the
	  profiles defined here and might be ignored by receiving systems.
	</p>
	<p>
	  There is <b>NO</b> expectation that instances conforming with this implementation guide will declare their conformance by asserting a <code>meta.profile</code>
	  value, though systems <b>MAY</b> choose to do so.  Systems <b>SHALL NOT</b> depend on the declaration of such profiles when consuming data.
	</p>
	
	<a name="terminology"> </a>
	<h4>Terminology expectations</h4>
	<p>
	  This implementation guide makes use of several external terminologies, including LOINC, SNOMED CT and CPT codes.  In
	  some places, the IG has identified the need for a code that does not yet exist in any of these external locations, but
	  which probably makes sense to be added to one of those code systems.  In this case, we have defined 'temporary' codes
	  in the <a href="CodeSystem-temporary-codes.html">temporary-codes</a>) Code system.  The location and value of these codes <b>WILL</b>
	  change in a future release of the specification.  Implementers should plan to accommodate this as part of their designs.
	</p>
	<p>
	  Some of the value sets referenced in this IG are not explicitly enumerated.  Instead, they are defined by filters on the underlying code systems.  Others are
	  maintained outside of the FHIR core specification and this IG.  In either case, this may result in the set of codes that are valid changing over time.
	  Systems <b>SHALL</b> allow for this potential evolution and <b>SHALL NOT</b> reject a code that might be valid unless they have an up-to-date copy of the
	  underlying code-system and value set definition.  Systems <b>SHOULD</b> ensure that their internal mappings are kept up-to-date as the list of available
	  codes change.
	</p>
</div>