<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">  <p>    This implementation guide defines a number of data sharing capabilities.  Some behaviors are tightly defined and will work    the same way in all evvironments (if all systems conform to this IG).  However, in many cases, a degree of variation is allowed.    This variation is necessary because of the breadth of types of implementation environments.  For example:  </p>  <ul>    <li>The participants involved in the exchange may vary - Only <a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-care-manager.html">Care Manager</a>      and <a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-patient-engagement.html">Patient Engagement</a> system, only Care Manager and      <a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-service-provider.html">Service Provider</a>, or all three.</li>    <li>The level of sophistication of the participants may vary - from a personal trainer using their phone, to a fitness center      that is partia</li>  </ul>  <h3>IG design process</h3>  <p>  </p>  <h3>Data storage location</h3>  <p>  </p>  <h3>Permissions for changing and creation</h3>  <p>  </p>  <h3>Implementation expectations</h3>  <p>    and what are the priorities  </p>  <h3>Value of electronic sharing with patients</h3>  <p>  </p>  <h3>Handling intermediaries</h3>  <p>  </p>  <h3>Support for </h3>  <p>    Todo - tradeoffs around storage locations for plans, goals, observations; who gets to update plans and goals; Subscription vs. polling; Discovering and configuring endpoints; Why there's so much flexibility in approach and what's implemented;    Ordered list of importance?  Level of communication via Task.  Non-messaging design  </p>      <li><b>Exercise prescriptions shareable</b> - While exercise prescriptions are useful, is there a value in sharing them electronically with      anyone, or is just printing it all that's needed?</li>    <li><b>Responsibilities of Service Provider</b> - Can Service Providers store data that is accessible to external systems?  Can they push       observations to care managers on behalf of a patient?  Can they update care plans or goals?  If so, do we want to standardize what changes       can and can't be made?</li>    <li><b>Responsibilities of Patient Engagement systems</b> - Can Patient systems store data that is accessible to external systems?        Can they update care plans or goals?  If so, do we want to standardize what changes can and can't be made?</li>    <li><b>Responsibilities of patient</b> - Can patient systems update goals and/or plans?</li>    <li><b>Condition needed</b> - following the Gravity SDOH pattern, they use Condition as the foundation for referrals, etc.  The logic is      that a formal diagnosis is needed to enable insurance billing.  Is that the case for physical activity, or can we get away with just      observations?  Do either Service Provider or Patient Engagement systems have any use for these?</li>    <li><b>Intermediaries?</b> - is there a role for intermediaries operating between care coordinators and Service Providers in the same way      that third parties function in Gravity SDOH?  If so, who would the likely candidates be and what would the business model be?</li>    <li><b>Feedback necessary?</b> - In Gravity, feedback about satisfaction with service providers is important to both ordering clinicians and      payers.  Are we confident that the same will be true in the physical activity space?  I.e. will systems bother asking for feedback about      service delivery, and if so, act on the information provided?  How?</li>    <li><b>Transaction support</b> - Where do we need to support sending multiple things at once in a transaction?  Is it better to      simply have all of the systems send resources one at a time?</li></div>