<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../input-cache/schemas/R4/fhir-xhtml.xsd">
  <p>
    This page summarizes the main changes that have happened between releases of the implementation guide
  </p>

  <a name="1.1.0"> </a>
  <h3>STU 1.1 - First official release (1.1.0)</h3>
  <p>
    Key changes in this release from the version that went to ballot are below.  Where applicable, links
    are included to the associated Jira issue.  In addition to these, a number of other non-substantive
    changes that clarify or improve wording and/or fix minor errors were applied.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Made support for the Coverage Information card mandatory (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-37484">FHIR-37484</a>)</li>
    <li>Made support for system action mandatory for coverage information and 'MAY' for request form completion and create/update coverage information (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-37484">FHIR-37484</a>)</li>
    <li>Dropped using SMART launch for DTR and deferred launch (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-33124">FHIR-33124</a>, <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-39452">FHIR-39452</a>)</li>
    <li>Additional changes to the coverage-information extension:
      <ul>
        <li>Add assertion of dependencies between a coverage assertion and other orders it might be dependent on  (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-40660">FHIR-40660</a>)</li>
        <li>Added support for questionnaires and responses coming back with coverage information, and guidance about how QRs should be represented  (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-40603">FHIR-40603</a>)</li>
        <li>Split the 'code' element into a number of properties that distinctly convey coverage, prior authorization, documentation requirements, need for additional information, etc.  As well, split the identifier into an assertion id and a prior auth satisfied id  (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41435">FHIR-41435</a>)</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Added guidance on metrics</li>
    <li>Added guidance on ePA coordinators</li>
  </ul>

  <a name="1.1.0-ballot"> </a>
  <h3>STU 1.1 - Ballot for second release (1.1.0-ballot)</h3>
  <p>
    Substantive changes in this release from the first official release are below.  Where applicable, links
    are included to the associated Jira issue.  In addition to these, a number of other non-substantive
    changes that clarify or improve wording and/or fix minor errors were applied.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Various updates to the coverage-information extension, including:
      <ul>
        <li>Added ability to link to which requests or other resources are associated with a card (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-33252">FHIR-33252</a>).</li>
        <li>Added a code to indicate the overall assertion (covered, not covered, prior auth required, clinical DTR needed, administrative DTR needed) - (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-33225">FHIR-33225</a>)</li>
        <li>Added link to the specific coverage the information applies to (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-33225">FHIR-33225</a>)</li>
        <li>Added date assertion was made (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-33225">FHIR-33225</a>)</li>
        <li>Added an identifier for traceability (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-33225">FHIR-33225</a>)</li>
        <li>Added 'reason' for the coverage assertion (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-36442">FHIR-36442</a>)</li>
        <li>Added a 'detail' structure to convey additional information about the coverage assertion  (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-36477">FHIR-36477</a>)</li>
        <li>Added ability to include a 'contact' for follow-up about a coverage assertion (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-37817">FHIR-37817</a>)</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Defined a standard list of card types (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-18895">FHIR-11895</a>)</li>
    <li>Add support for system action as an optional sharing approach (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-34216">FHIR-34216</a>)</li>
    <li>Added rules requiring hooks to only be sent to payers where patient has active coverage (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-34102">FHIR-34102</a>)</li>
    <li>Removed mustSupport from the 'insurance' elements in the various Request resources, as well as dropping the extension introduced to those resources that did not have an 'insurance' element (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-36746">FHIR-36746</a>)</li>
  </ul>

  <a name="1.0.0"> </a>
  <h3>STU 1 - First official release (1.0.0)</h3>
  <p>
    Key changes in this release from the version that went to ballot are below.  Where applicable, links
    are included to the associated Jira issue.  In addition to these, a number of other non-substantive
    changes that clarify or improve wording and/or fix minor errors were applied.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Updated CapabilityStatements to be based on US Core and revised conformance expectations for many of the operations.  Also added expectations on Patient, Practitioner and other registry resources (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-40796">FHIR-40796</a>, <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-40767">FHIR-40767</a>, <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-40751">FHIR-40751</a>)</li>
    <li>For the different profiles, use 'activity' rather than 'social history' as the category to satisfy US Core and make the Physical Activity category mandatory (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41295">FHIR-41295</a>, <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41114">FHIR-41114</a>, <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41037">FHIR-41037</a>, <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-40776">FHIR-40776</a>)</li>
    <li>For the different observations, remove the prohibition on Observation.bodySite (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41086">FHIR-41086</a>)</li>
    <li>Added 'patient experience' to the set of activity measures (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41362">FHIR-41362</a>)</li>
    <li>Added average heart rate as an activity measure (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-40952">FHIR-40952</a>)</li>
    <li>Tightened the condition statuses to those relevant for physical activity (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41362">FHIR-41362</a>)</li>
    <li>For goal, require at least one of description and target, tighten expectations on Quantity, and allow pointing to any physical activity measure codes (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41294">FHIR-41294</a>)</li>
    <li>For DiagnosticReport, made the report type extensible (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41293">FHIR-41293</a>)</li>
    <li>For ServiceRequest, added a 'notes' section, constrained allowed statuses, made authoredOn and requester mandatory, and require either reasonCode or reasonReference (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41291">FHIR-41291</a>)</li>
    <li>For Task for Referral, made Task.reason, Task.owner and Task.requester 1..1 (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41295">FHIR-41295</a>, <a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41206">FHIR-41206</a>)</li>
    <li>For RelatedPerson, set conformance expectations for elements in telecom and address (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41295">FHIR-41295</a>)</li>
    <li>For subscription, change to use the official R4 code (<a href="https://jira.hl7.org/browse/FHIR-41053">FHIR-41053</a>)</li>
  </ul>
    

  <a name="1.0.0-ballot"> </a>
  <h3>STU 1 ballot - First ballot (1.0.0-ballot)</h3>
	<p>
    This was the first version of the specification intended for ballot review.  It included the physical
    activity vital signs, the initial set of time-based and activity-based measures, as well as support for
    goals, planns, and referral workflow.
  </p>
</div>
