<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R4/fhir-single.xsd">
	<p>
    This page defines the mechanisms providers can use to assist patients with their physical activvity levels if measurements indicate
    that intervention is called for.  There are three main mechanisms defined:
	</p>
	<ul>
    <li>creating <a href="orders">exercise prescriptions</a> detailing what level of physical activity a patient should performing on
      a regular basis</li>
    <li>setting <a href="plans">plans and goals</a> with the patient and their supports around what their physical activity level should
      look like - and how they can realistically get there, and</li>
    <li>creating <a href="referrals">referrals</a> to physical activity specialists who can help a patient to achieve their
      physical activity targets in a manner that meets their physical limitations, lifestyle and interests</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    These three types of interventions can be used separately or in concert to help patients achieve a healthy level of physical activity.
  </p>
  
  <a name="orders"> </a>
  <h3>Exercise Prescriptions</h3>
  <p>
    Sometimes all that's necessary to help a patient to improve their level of physicial activity is to have their clinician formally
    prescribe it, in much the same way as they might prescribe a medication or physiotherapy.  [Todo - add references to literature supporting
    this.]
  </p>
  <p>
    In FHIR, orders for physical actions are represented using the <a href="StructureDefinition-pa-servicerequest.html">ServiceRequest profile</a>.
    In the case of an exercise referral, the ServiceRequest 'performer' would be the patient themselves.  The requested activity would be
    exercise therapy (SNOMED 229065009), possibly with more specific textual details as to the type of physical activity to perform, along
    with timing information - e.g. 150 minutes/week conveyed in the effectiveTiming element.
  </p>
  <p>
    While in many cases there is no need for such orders to be exchanged electronically, it may be useful for others involved in the patient's
    care to be aware of the existence of the order so they can support the patient in performing it.
  </p>

  <a name="plans"> </a>
  <h3>Plans and Goals</h3>
  <p>
    
  </p>

  <a name="referrals"> </a>
  <h3>Referrals</h3>
</div>
