<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R4/fhir-single.xsd">
  <p>
    Having a standardized way of measuring patient physical activity - and sharing those measurements - is an essential step to improving physical activity levels, both at an
    individual and at a population level.  Standard measures are needed to:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>consistently evaluate whether a patient's activity levels are adequate for good health</li>
    <li>monitor trends to determine whether activity levels are improving (particularly in response to an intervention) or possibly declining (e.g. due to a health condition or
	  other intervention)</li>
    <li>allow coordination of care with a shared understanding of activity level between clinicians, patients and community-based service providers who can help patients assume a 
      more physically active lifestyle and stay motivated</li>
    <li>form a basis for researchers interested in the correlation between physical activity level and health outcomes, as well as in which interventions are most effective in boosting 
      physical activity levels and associated outcomes</li>
    <li>allow de-identified information to flow into national or regional surveillance systems, such as public health.  This information can then inform programming, evidence-based 
      policy and funding to address physical activity level challenges within certain communities or demographics</li>
    <li>support evidence-based reumeration of community-based physical activity professionals who support at risk patients in improving their activity levels </li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    This page describes standards for representing observations about a patient with respect to their level of physical activity as well
    as supporting observations that provide additional detail and evidence for those higher-level observations.
  </p>
  <a name="base"> </a>
  <h3>Base measure</h3>
	<p>
    The foundational step in improving physical activity levels is having an agreed measure consistently used across EHRs to capture a
    patient's level of physical activity.  There are a wide variety of different types of physical activity and numerous different ways
    of capturing what activities were performed, and varying granularities with which the data can be captured.
	</p>
	<p>
	  While fine-grained and detailed records (e.g. exactly which type of exercise was performed, which muscle groups were activated, how
	  many repetitions were performed, how many intervals were done, etc.) are important for certain types of therapy and for research
	  purposes, they are too complex and onerous for wide-spread use and are not easily evaluatable from a perspective of "is this patient
	  sufficiently active to maintain good health?"
	</p>
	<p>
	  This guide therefore mandates a slightly modified version of the very simple Exercise Vital Sign (LOINC <a href="https://loinc.org/89574-8/">89574-8</a> 
	  as the primary measure of patient physical activity level for exchange and evaluation.  The <a href="background.html#pa-measure">background page</a>
	  provides details on the evidence that supports this measure as accurate and appropriate for evaluating how well a patient meets guidalines for
	  physical activity.
	</p>
	<p>
	  The measure consists of two questions:
	</p>
	<ul>
    <li>For an average week in the last 30 days, how many days per week did you engage in moderate to strenuous exercise (like walking fast,
      running, jogging, dancing, swimming, biking, or other activities that cause a light or heavy sweat)?</li>
    <li>On those days that you engage in moderate to strenuous exercise, how many minutes, on average, do you exercise?</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    These two questions correspond to the LOINC codes <a href="https://loinc.org/89555-7">89555-7</a> and 
    <a href="https://loinc.org/68516-4">68516-4</a>.  In this implementation guide, there are profiles to capture the answers to each of these 
    questions - the <a href="StructureDefinition-observation-evs-days-per-week.html">days-per-week</a> and 
    <a href="StructureDefinition-observation-evs-min-per-day.html">min-per-day</a> profiles.  (Examples of Observations that comply with these
    two profiles can be found <a href="Observation-ExampleEVSMinutesPerDay.html">here</a> and 
    <a href="Observation-ExampleEVSDaysPerWeek.html">here</a>.)
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>TO CONFIRM:</b>
    While these two questions are logically part of a single overall <a href="https://loinc.org/89574-8">89574-8</a> observation, this guide  
    does not require the capture or sharing higher-level grouping observations that link the the answers to the two key questions.
  </p>
  <p>
    In addition, this guide captures two additional measures:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>The product of the two EVS measures, giving an average amount of exercise in minutes/week (and captured using LOINC code 
      <a href="https://loinc.org/82290-8">82290-8</a>)</li>
    <li>An indication of the amount of strength-based exercises a patient has perform, expressed as days/week (and captured using
      LOINC code <a href="https://loinc.org/82291-6">82291-6</a>)</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    While the first of these is theoretically redundant with the two EVS measures, this calculated minutes/week measure is the one that is
    actually compared against national guidelines to determine whether a patient has adequate physical activity or not.  As such, having
    it explicitly captured and stored allows for easier searching, trending and diagnosis.
  </p>
  <p>
    The second measure allows evaluation of the patient against guidelines for strength-based exercise specifically.  
  </p>
  <p>
    If a system does not wish to support directly capturing the answers to these key measures as Observations but is able to handle
    filling out a FHIR Questionnaire, this IG also defines a standard <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.sdc}}">Structured Data Capture</a>
    Questionnaire instance that includes the relevant metadata to allow automated extraction of a completed QuestionnaireResponse
    into the relevant Observations using either the 
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.sdc}}/extraction.html#observation-based-extraction">observation-based</a> or 
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.sdc}}/extraction.html#structuremap-based-extraction">StructureMap-based</a> approach.  The
    Questionnaire is <a href="Questionnaire-questionnaire-evs.html">here</a>.  An example QuestionnaireResponse that would correspond to the
    examples listed above can be found <a href="QuestionnaireResponse-qr-evs-example.html">here</a>.
  </p>
  
  
  <a name="support"> </a>
  <h3>Supporting measures</h3>
  <p>
    While it is certainly possible for patients and their care-givers to estimate their average days/week and minutes/day of moderate to
    high-intensity exercise, relying exclusively on estimates is not necessarily ideal.  Therefore, capturing additional information about
    physicial activity can be helpful.  This information may assist the patient in the creation of their estimates.  They can also be used
    to provide clinicians and exercise professionals with more granular information to provide better insight into the patient's current
    exercise regime.  Potential supplemental measures include:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Step counts,</li>
    <li>Heartrate measurements,</li>
    <li>Daily activity logs,</li>
    <li>Others?</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    However, there are challenges with these measures.  Continuous measures that capture heart rates on a per-minute or
    even a per-second basis can create an immense load of data that most clinical systems will not be able to (or at least wish to)
    manage.  As a result, average measures are more useful.  At the same time, an average heart rate over the course of a day is not
    terribly helpful either.  20 minutes of elevated heart-rate due to exercise simply blends in and becomes difficult to distinguish.
    In the same way, a total count of 20,000 steps per day indicates a certain level of activity.  However, whether they constitute
    "moderate to strenuous" exercise is hard to determine.  The same count of steps could represent an hour of jogging, or a day spent
    pacing while talking on the phone.  Both are better than sitting, but only one would count as "moderate to strenuous" exercise.
  </p>
  <p>
    For these reasons, this implementation guide places limits on the types of supporting measurements systems are expected to share.
    Systems are free to share raw measures and more fine-grained data if they choose, but there is no expectation within this implementation
    guide for systems to support sharing information beyond that described below - and even support for these supplemental data elements are 
    optional.
  </p>
  <p>
    An additional consideration is that capture of steps, heart rate, or even daily electronic activity logs requires that patients have
    access to electronic devices to capture such measurements.  This won't be possible for all patients.  Therefore, systems <b>SHOULD NOT</b>
    set any requirements for the inclusion of these finer-grained measures unless steps have been taken to eliminate patient accessibility
    barriers.
  </p>
  <p>
    The following observation profiles can be used to capture supplemental measurements.  All of these measurements can be linked from the
    base exercise vital sign measure via the 'derivedFrom' relationship, indicating that the 30-day vital sign was derived from, in part,
    the detailed measurement.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="StructureDefinition-observation-sup-daily.html">Daily Exercise Log</a></li>  
    <li><a href="StructureDefinition-observation-sup-hr.html">Average Heart Rate</a></li>  
    <li><a href="StructureDefinition-observation-sup-steps.html">Average Step Count</a></li>  
  </ul>
  <p>
    <b>Note:</b> The exercise time asserted in the overall exercise vital sign will not necessarily mathematically align with the times indicated
    by the supporting measurements.  A patient may assert exercise that is not supported by a fine-grained measurement.  Also, some of the
    fine-grained measurements may not correspond to time the patient considers to have been moderate to strenuous exercise.  The purpose of
    the supporting measurements is to assist the patient or caregiver in making their estimates as accurate as possible and to assist 
    practitioners in understanding more about the nature and timing of the patient's exercise.
  </p>
  <h4>Device-based measures</h4>
  <p>
    Measures such as step counts and heart rates will almost always come from personal healthcare devices.  However, these devices won't
    (typically) capture their data as average.  Instead, there will be periodic measurements with a number of steps over a short interval
    or a heart rate at a specific point in time.  The averages will therefore typically need to be captured by the patient's physical
    activity tracking application.  It will do this by looking at the device-reported data and then capturing the average values - or
    more specifically, the average values for those time periods that appear to be relevant to physical activity.
  </p>
  <p>
    This guide does not define data standards for the raw device-based data.  HL7 has a <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/uv/phd">Personal
    Healthcare Devices</a> that provides a mechanism for raw device measurements to be exposed as FHIR.  In many cases, it may be simpler
    to leverage the Apple Healthkit or Android Fit APIs to access the fine-grained measurements in order to determine the relevant averages.
  </p>
</div>
