<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R4/fhir-single.xsd">
  <a name="base"> </a>
  <h3>Base measure</h3>
	<p>
    The foundational step in improving physical activity levels is having an agreed measure consistently used across EHRs to capture a
    patient's level of physical activity.  There are a wide variety of different types of physical activity and numerous different ways
    of capturing what activities were performed, and varying granularities with which the data can be captured.
	</p>
	<p>
	  While fine-grained and detailed records (e.g. exactly which type of exercise was performed, which muscle groups were activited, how
	  many repetitions were performed, how many intervals were done, etc.) are important for certain types of therapy and for research
	  purposes, they are too complex and onerous for wide-spread use and are not easily evaluatable from a perspective of "is this patient
	  sufficiently active to maintain good health?"
	</p>
	<p>
	  This guide therefore mandates the use of the very simple Exercise Vital Sign (LOINC <a href="https://loinc.org/89574-8/">89574-8</a> 
	  as the primary measure of patient physical activity level for exchange and evaluation.  This measure [is super awesome because all this
	  research says it works great - Laurie please provide text to fill in here].
	</p>
	<p>
	  The measure consists of two questions:
	</p>
	<ul>
    <li>For an average week in the last 30 days, how many days per week did you engage in moderate to strenuous exercise (like walking fast,
      running, jogging, dancing, swimming, biking, or other activities that cause a light or heavy sweat)?</li>
    <li>On those days that you engage in moderate to strenuous exercise, how many minutes, on average, do you exercise?</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    These two questions correspond to the LOINC codes <a href="https://loinc.org/89555-7">89555-7</a> and 
    <a href="https://loinc.org/68516-4">68516-4</a>.  In this implementation guide, there are profiles to capture the answers to each of these 
    questions - the <a href="StructureDefinition-observation-evs-days-per-week.html">days-per-week</a> and 
    <a href="StructureDefinition-observation-evs-min-per-day.html">min-per-day</a> profiles.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>TO CONFIRM:</b>
    While these two questions are logically part of a single overall <a href="https://loinc.org/89574-8">89574-8</a> observation, this guide  
    does not require the capture or sharing higher-level grouping observations that link the the answers to the two key questions.
  </p>
  <a name="support"> </a>
  <h3>Supporting measures</h3>
  <p>
    While it's certainly possible for patients and their care-givers to estimate their average days/week and minutes/day of moderate to
    high-intensity exercise, relying exclusively on estimates is not necessarily ideal.  Therefore, capturing additional information about
    physicial activity can be helpful.  This information may assist the patient in the creation of their estimates.  They can also be used
    to provide clinicians and exercise professionals with more granular information to provide better insight into the patient's current
    exercise regime.  Potential supplemental measures include:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Step counts,</li>
    <li>Heartrate measurements,</li>
    <li>Pulse-ox measurements,</li>
    <li>Daily activity logs,</li>
    <li>Others?</li>
  </ul>
</div>
