<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <p>
    This implementation guide is <b>>DRAFT</b>.  There are a number of open issues that will need to be resolved before it will be fully 
    implementable and a number of additional clean-up steps that will need to be taken before the guide is published for ballot.
    A list of known issues follows.  If there are additional issues you feel should be discussed/addressed, please raise them on the 
    <a href="https://chat.fhir.org/#narrow/stream/327137-Physical-Activity">project discussion stream</a> on http://chat.fhir.org.
  </p>
  <h3>Open issues</h3>
  <p>
    These are topics that will require debate and discussion with domain experts to determine how the specification should work.  Project calls
    will focus on resolving these issues.
  </p>
  <ol>
    <li><b>General approach</b> - this specification was developed without broad review by domain experts and therefore may not meet real
      needs and/or may include functionality that is not needed or unlikely to be implemented.  A thorough review and potentially
      exploration of alternatives is needed</li>
    <li><b>EVS Grouping</b> - The spec currently says that exercise vital sign doesn't need to have a high-level grouping and represents
      each of the components as distinct observations.  Is this the appropriate representation?</li>
    <li><b>Additional primary meassures</b> -  Do we want any additional 'primary' measures - e.g. ones that distinguish aerobic from 
      strength-based exercise and/or that drill down into the specific details of the type(s) of exercise performed?  Alternatively,
      do we want to support additional 'properties' that further qualify the high level EVS observations (e.g. exercise types)?
      Considerations include: What's the evidence to support?, Can we realistically expect most patients to capture? and Can we expect most 
      clinicians/professionals to make use of the additional data?</li>
    <li><b>Supporting measures</b> - Do we have the right ones?  Will clincians actually care about this data?  Can apps really use it to
      help patients fill in their EVS measures?  Are there other measures we're missing?</li>
    <li><b>Fine-grained measures</b> - the guide assumes that the patient *won't* be sharing their individual heart rate, step count and other
      measurements, as that would represent way too much volume.  Is this a reasonable assumption?</li>
    <li><b>Plans and prescriptions?</b> - is there sufficient difference in value between having an exercise prescription and having a 
      plan that we need to support both?</li>
    <li><b>Exercise prescriptions shareable</b> - While exercise prescriptions are useful, is there a value in sharing them electronically with
      anyone, or is just printing it all that's needed?</li>
    <li><b>Responsibilities of Service Provider</b> - Can Service Providers store data that is accessible to external systems?  Can they push 
      observations to care managers on behalf of a patient?  Can they update care plans or goals?  If so, do we want to standardize what changes 
      can and can't be made?</li>
    <li><b>Responsibilities of Patient Engagement systems</b> - Can Service Providers store data that is accessible to external systems?  
      Can they update care plans or goals?  If so, do we want to standardize what changes can and can't be made?</li>
    <li><b>Intervention types</b> - The current list of possible interventions are the codes that exist in SNOMED CT that seem to be relevant,
      however that doesn't mean that they're useful.  What codes should actually exist?  What codes are necessary to provide an appropriate
      level of computability, particularly for billing support?</li>
    <li><b>Responsibilities of patient</b> - Can patient systems update goals and/or plans?</li>
    <li><b>Condition needed</b> - following the Gravity SDOH pattern, they use Condition as the foundation for referrals, etc.  The logic is
      that a formal diagnosis is needed to enable insurance billing.  Is that the case for physical activity, or can we get away with just
      observations?  Do either Service Provider or Patient Engagement systems have any use for these?</li>
    <li><b>Intermediaries?</b> - is there a role for intermediaries operating between care coordinators and Service Providers in the same way
      that third parties function in Gravity SDOH?  If so, who would the likely candidates be and what would the business model be?</li>
    <li><b>Feedback necessary?</b> - In Gravity, feedback about satisfaction with service providers is important to both ordering clinicians and
      payers.  Are we confident that the same will be true in the physical activity space?  I.e. will systems bother asking for feedback about
      service delivery, and if so, act on the information provided?  How?</li>
    <li><b>Transaction support</b> - Where do we need to support sending multiple things at once in a transaction?  Is it better to
      simply have all of the systems send resources one at a time?</li>
    <li><b>Registry management</b> - The ordering, performing and possibly patient systems will need to have a shared authoritative list of
      entities that can be referred to, including an ability to filter the regestry entries to those that are 'relevant'.  Ideally, we'll be
      able to leverage the work from [FAST Directory Query IG](build.fhir.org/ig/HL7/fhir-directory-query/), though that doesn't cover everything
      we need.  Specific entities that will need to be discoverable and referenceable include:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}">CareTeam</a>? - if used to represent a team of practitioners with assigned roles</li>
        <li>HealthcareService - if used to represent particular capabilities a patient can be referred to</li>
        <li>Organization - to identify clinical, social service, and intervention delivery organizations</li>
        <li>Patient - the focus of the observations and beneficiary of any interventions</li>
        <li>Practitioner and PractitionerRole - specific individuals involved in planning and ordering care or delivering care</li>
        <li>RelatedPerson - parents, spouses, neighbors and others who may act on behalf of the patient and/or assist the patient</li>
      </ul>
      Of these, neither Patient nor RelatedPerson are covered by the FAST project, so alternatives will need to be explored.  For the remainder,
      will need to confirm which ones will be used and whether we can leverage existing registry endpoints (and get additional relevant
      practitioners, organizations, etc. exposed and managed via those endpoints).
    </li>
    <li><b>Subscriptions</b> - Gravity makes use of subscriptions to monitor for changes to orders and tasks.  Is that something we want to do too?
      Doing so requires a larger degree of system capability.  It also requires using R4B rather than R4, and R4B isn't yet referenced in 
      U.S. regulations.</li>
    <li><b>Examples</b> - every profile we have needs to have at least one, and ideally several examples that cover the range of how it can be
      used.  Most ideal of all would be for the examples to interrelate and convey a realistic scenario.  We need to gather the scenarios and
      the detailed data elements that would be shared in those scenarios in order to construct appropriate examples.</li>
    <li><b>Implementation</b> - We cannot bring this specification to ballot until multiple independent systems have implemnted it and successfully
      interoperated in at least a test environment.  Who will implement and who can they test with?</li>
    <li><b>MVP?</b> - Do the conformance requirements reflect the 'minimum viable product' needed by the market with optional elements limited to
      those that, while not strictly necessary, are still likely to be taken up by a significant proportion of the community?</li>
    <li>Should the IG support access to guidelines around "how best to discuss?", "how best to intervene?", "what are common barriers to explore?"</li>
    <li>How do clinicians find out what services are available - do we need something more than just registries</li>
    <li>Should we flag 'validated' observations (i.e. where a professional was watching, gathered from device)</li>
  </ol>
  <h3>Outstanding to-do items</h3>
  <p>
    These are known deficiencies in the specification that need to be corrected, but which don't necessarily require domain expertise to
    address.  Some of them are technical and relate to HL7 internal processes, so don't worry if you don't understand them all.
  </p>
  <ol>
    <li>Add a security and privacy section</li>
    <li>Artifacts: Create initial examples for all profiles</li>
    <li>Various: Create diagrams to represent information visually where it makes sense to</li>
    <li>Explain why our Questionnaires aren't using StructureMap-based extraction the way Gravity SDOH does</li>
    <li>Transaction: Set expectations for support of transaction in measure submission and possibly interventions</li>
    <li>Downloads: Remove link to backport IG if we're not using it.</li>
    <li>Artifacts: Create complete examples (and possibly ExampleScenarios) for all profiles leveraging domain epxert input</li>
    <li>Credits: add list of active project participants</li>
    <li>Everywhere: Full spelling and grammer check, plus review for clarity and readability (feel free to report issues you find though!)</li>
    <li>QA Report: Create Jira file</li>
    <li>QA Report: Seek US Realm exceptions for non-US-Core-derived profiles</li>
    <li>QA Report: Make sure it's clean</li>
  </ol>
</div>
