<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R4/fhir-single.xsd">
  <p>
    This implementation guide is <b>DRAFT</b>.  There are a number of open issues that will need to be resolved before it will be fully 
    implementable and a number of additional clean-up steps that will need to be taken before the guide is published for ballot.
    A list of known issues follows.  If there are additional issues you feel should be discussed/addressed, please raise them on the 
    <a href="https://chat.fhir.org/#narrow/stream/327137-Physical-Activity">project discussion stream</a> on http://chat.fhir.org.
  </p>
  <a name="openissues"> </a>
  <h3>Open issues</h3>
  <p>
    These are topics that will require debate and discussion with domain experts to determine how the specification should work.  Project calls
    will focus on resolving these issues.
  </p>
  <ol>
    <li>Continue reviewing CapabilityStatement expectations and profile expectations</li>
    <li>Detailed walkthrough of data models</li>
    <li>Create Confluence page with list of organizations that can provide guidelines for how best to engage with
      patients around improving physical activity </li>
  </ol>
  <a name="todo"> </a>
  <h3>Outstanding to-do items</h3>
  <p>
    These are known deficiencies in the specification that need to be corrected, but which don't necessarily require domain expertise to
    address.  Some of them are technical and relate to HL7 internal processes, so don't worry if you don't understand them all.
  </p>
  <ol>
    <li>Various: Create diagrams to represent information visually where it makes sense to; in particular a diagram showing systems and relationships, how to do subscriptions</li>
    <li>Add more and more diverse images to document</li>
    <li>Artifacts: Create complete examples (and possibly ExampleScenarios) for all profiles leveraging domain expert input</li>
    <li>Everywhere: Review for clarity and readability (feel free to report issues you find though!)</li>
    <li>Update US Realm approval on RelatedPerson</li>
    <li>Add maturity levels</li>
    <li>Fix subscriptions search</li>
    <li>Ensure Figure labels are unique and sequential (and maybe create a table of them?)</li>
  </ol>
</div>
