<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <p>
    While exercise-related information is typically less sensitive than most healthcare information, it is still considered to be protected healthcare
    information.  As such, the data sharing enabledy by this IG requires authentication, authorization, and secure transport.
  </p>
  <p>
    Implementers of this IG are expected to adhere to the same security and privacy rules as are <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.sdoh}}/privacy_and_security.html">defined
    in the Gravity IG</a>.  Gravity allows several alternative authentication mechanisms, however in the near-term, implementers of this IG are strongly encouraged
    to use the <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/smart-app-launch/2023Jan/app-launch.html">SMART App Launch</a> mechanism for user-mediated interactions (e.g. 
    interactions from a <a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-patient-engagement.html">Patient Engagement</a> system or 
    <a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-service-provider-light.html">Light Service Provider</a>) and
    <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/smart-app-launch/2023Jan/backend-services.html">SMART Backend Services</a> for system-to-system interactions that do not
    necessarily involve human intervention (e.g. between a <a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-care-manager.html">Care Manager</a> and a 
    <a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-service-provider-full.html">Full Service Provider</a>).
  </p>
  
  <a name="consent"> </a>
  <h3>Consent</h3>
  <p>
    Many of the exercise professionals and exercise organizations that will be <a href="workflow.html#serviceprovider">Service Providers</a> in this IG fall outside 
    the bounds of "Covered Entities" from a HIPAA perspective.  As such, consent will typically be required in order for referrals, plans, goals, observations, etc.
    to be shared from clinical systems.  In addition, consent will often be needed if patient information is to be shared with a patient's caregivers.  It is the 
    responsibility of each organization and provider to ensure that consent is gathered when necessary and that disclosures are conducted in compliance with the
    consents on file.
  </p>
  <p>
    This specification does not set expectations for sharing consent information because, at present, it does not envision the use of
    <a href="design.html#intermediaries">intermediaries</a> and that would be the primary reason why other systems would need to have an awareness of what
    consent(s) had been granted.  For implementers who do make use of intermediaries, conveying consent as 
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.sdoh}}exchange_workflow.html#workflow-and-managing-consent">described</a> by the Gravity SDOH IG should be workable.
  </p>
  
  <a name="shared"> </a>
  <h3>Shared or Delegated Access</h3>
  <p>
    In implementations where caregivers are involved in accessing and/or reporting patient information via <i>Patient Engagement</i> systems, those systems
    <b>SHOULD</b> be designed to allow each caregiver to authenticate independently and track what information is accessed, created, or updated by which
    individual.  Unless both <i>Care Managers</i> and <i>Service Providers</i> maintain a shared or synchronized authorization server that tracks patient
    delegated access, such users will need to be configured independently for each system they have access to.
  </p>
  
  <a name="access"> </a>
  <h3>Access Management</h3>
  <p>
    This specification relies on RESTful searches to allow retrieval of data from other systems.  When a <i>Service Provider</i> searches for observations,
    goals, plans, etc. on a <i>Care Manager</i>, it is unlikely that they will (or should) have access to all data available.  It is the responsibility of
    all systems acting as a data source to ensure that the data consumer <i>only</i> has access to the patient records and the data from within those
    records that is appropriate for the type of care they are offering.  In some cases, that may include information beyond what is defined in this IG.
    For example, it may be appropriate (with patient consent) to disclose to an exercise professional that a patient is taking an ACE inhibitor, is
    diabetic, etc.  It is up to organizational policy, in conjunction with regulation and patient preferences, to determine what data should be made
    available.  As discussed in the <a href="design.html">Design</a> section, <a href="design.html#categories">Categories</a> may prove to be a helpful
    mechanism to assist in filtering, but they are not the only option, and may not be sufficient for all filtering that needs to be performed.
  </p>
</div>
