<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R4/fhir-single.xsd">
	<p>
    This section of the specification talks about the different types systems and the specific workflows covered by this implementation guide.
  </p>
  <p>
    NOTE: Additional systems and/or workflows may be introduced in the future.  E.g. anonymized reporting, quality metric assessment, etc.
  </p>

	<a name="actors"> </a>
  <h3>Actors</h3>
  <p>
    There are three specific types of systems that cooperate to help manage and improve patient physical activity levels.  They are:
	</p>
	<ul>
    <li><a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-care-manager.html">Care Managers</a> are electronic health record or similar systems used by physicians, 
      social workers, or others who have general responsibility for care of the patient.  These are the systems that will perform initial
      data capture, whose users may identify an issue with physical activity level, and will coordinate any interventions to improve
      physical activity level.</li>
    <li><a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-patient-engagement.html">Patient Engagment Apps</a> are systems that will be used by patients and/or their care givers
      to capture data to share with clinicians and physical activity specialists.  They will also allow patients and their representatives
      to see and potentially update plans of care related to physical activity.</li>
    <li><a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-referral-recipient.html">Referral Recipients</a> are systems used by physical activity professionals,
      such as personal trainers, community fitness centers, etc. who can provide services to patients to enhance and maintain their levels
      of physical activity.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    NOTE: Not all scenarios will necessarily involve all three types of systems.  For example:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Some patients will not have access to (or interest in using) a monitoring app and communication will solely be between the Care
       Manager and Referral Recipient systems.</li>
    <li>Some patients may not be interested in (or require) a referral to external exercise professionals and all interactions will take
      place solely between the Care Manager and Patient Engagement Apps.</li>
    <li>In some cases, Care Managers will act alone and not interact with other systems, though exposing their records over FHIR interfaces
      will still enable care transitions and other data sharing.</li>
  </ul>
  
  <h3>Workflows</h3>
  <p>
    This implementation guide covers two main workflows: <a href="#plans">Care planning</a> and <a href="#referral">Referral management</a>.
    Both are heavily informed by the workflows described in the 
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.sdoh}}/sdoh_clinical_care_scope.html">Gravity SDOH IG</a>.  However, these flows and their associated
    artifacts have been adapted to reflect the needs of the physical activity space.
  </p>
  <p>
    NOTE: These workflows will frequently make reference to the 'patient' being involved in the process - as a source of data, as a
    participant in care planning, as a participant in interventions, etc.  In almost all circumstances, this should be read as 
    "the patient and/or their care giver(s)".  Information might be gathered from parents, guardians, or any other trusted person who
    has responsibility for the patient's care and/or are otherwise supporting the patient in meeting their healthcare objectives.  This 
    can even include caregivers being the focus of interventions, for example receiving training so they can better assist the patient in 
    the execution of their exercise plan.
  </p>
  
  <a name="plans"> </a>
  <h4>Physical Activity Care Planning</h4>
  <p>
    Care planning around physical activity follows a 'loop' pattern similar to all clinical care planning:
  </p>
  <ol>
    <li>The patient is assessed to determine if there is an issue to be addressed.</li>
    <li>If an issue is found, the care provider works with the patient to determine a goal or set of goals to improve the current state and a plan to meet them</li>
    <li>The care provider and patient then work together to come up with a plan to meet those goals, possibly involving external interventions</li>
    <li>From time to time, the care provider and patient touch base to evaluate progress and, as necessary, make adjustments to the plan and goals</li>
  </ol>
  <p>
    This may continue until the issue is deemed 'resolved' or until the patient determines they no longer wish to address the issue.  Alternatively,
    it may continue indefinitely, even when a target state has been reached, just to monitor and ensure ongoing success.
  </p>
  <p>Breaking these steps up into more detail</p>
  
  <a name="diagnosis"> </a>
  <h5>Issue identification</h5>
  <p>
    Some models might refer to this as 'diagnosis', but that word can be somewhat charged with connotations around 'who' is permitted to
    make such decisions.  In the context of this implementation guide, no specific rules are established around who 'authorized' to determine
    that a patient's level of physical activity is problematic.  However, some insurance plans or programs may introduce such expectations in order
    to authorize payment for interventions.
  </p>
  <p>
    U.S. Health and Human Services provides the following minimum recommendations for physical activity for Americans:
  </p>
  <table style="grid">
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th>Age group</th>
        <th>Target activity level</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>6-17 years</td>
        <td>60 minutes/day moderate-vigorous activity</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Adults</td>
        <td>150-300 minutes/week moderate or 75-150 minutes/week of vigorous activity</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <p>
    However, the fundamental determination of when intervention is appropriate is left up
    to care providers and patients to determine.  Comorbidities such as diabetes, hypertension, obesity, cardiac risk factors, etc. may all
    come into play, either indicating that higher target levels or sometimes lower target levels are appropriate.  Payers may set rules for
    what criteria need to be met in order for interventions to be covered under particular plans.
  </p>
  <p>
    One key part of the preceding paragraph is that care providers and patients <i>together</i> make a determination as to whether a problem
    exists and requires intervention.  The cycle of setting goals, planning steps to achieve those goals and monitoring progress can only occur
    if the patient is on-board.  Absent that, a clinician can only note their concern in the chart, councel the patient, and follow up on
    subsequent visits to see if readiness may have changed.
  </p>
  <p>
    Typically the identification of an issue will begin with the capture of an exercise vital sign - either directly as observations
    (i.e. <a href="StructureDefinition-observation-evs-days-per-week.html">days/week</a> and 
    <a href="StructureDefinition-observation-evs-min-per-day.html">min/day</a>), using a 
    <a href="Questionnaire-questionnaire-evs.html">small Questionnaire</a>, or possibly incorporating those same questions as part of a larger 
    questionnaire (e.g. using <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.sdc}}/modular.html">modular forms</a>).  This information might be recorded directly
    by the patient or by the care provider based on information solicited from the patient.
  </p>
  <p>
    If the care provider believes the patient's exercise level is problematic for their long-term health, they might choose to record a
    <a href="StructureDefinition-pa-condition.html">Condition</a> in the record indicating their concern, and to act as a focal point for subsequent
    plans, goals, and interventions.
  </p>
  <p>
    In this IG, creation or updating of a Condition is always done internally by a Care Manager.  However, external systems (i.e. Refererral Recipients
    and Patient Engagement systems can search for and retrieve these records.
  </p>
  
  <a name="plan"> </a>
  <p>
    The planning step involves coming to agreement with the patient about what their target should be for exercise frequency and duration, possibly
    with sub-targets along the way, as well as target timeframes for meeting those objectives.  Then the two need to agree on what steps will best help 
    the patient to get their exercise levels into the desired duration and frequency target range.  Historically, this plan would typically have been 
    captured as encounter notes within the care provider's system.  However, this guide sets higher expectations.
   </p>
   <p>
    To ensure appropriate ongoing coordination between care provider, patient, and exercise professionals, both the plan and any associated goals
    need to be shareable in a standardized manner.  The <a href="StructureDefinition-pa-careplan.html">exercise plan</a> is a simple structure 
    that captures the date, patient, author and a textual narrative describing the proposed plan the patient will follow.  Systems are free to
    capture and share additional discrete information if they wish, but only the minimum set of data described in this IG's profile need to be
    supported.  In some cases, the plan shared may carry more information than just information about exercise.  However, the plan <b>SHOULD</b>
    not contain any information that would be inappropriate for exercise professionals or others involved in the patient's exercise plan to see.
  </p>
  <p>
    The exercise plan will almost always be accompanied by <a href="StructureDefinition-pa-goal.html">physical activity goals</a>.  These express
    targets for the patient in a computable manner such that Patient Engagement systems can render a patient's progress against their goals and
    all participants in the patient's care can have a shared understanding of what goals have been met, what goals are still being worked towards
    and what is intended for the future.
  </p>
  <p>
    In this IG, the expectation is that both the exercise plan and its associated goals are stored on the Care Manager.  At minimum, Referral Recipient
    and Patient Engagement systems will be able to query and monitor the plan and goals.  In some environments, they may also be able to make changes
    to plans and goals, such as adjusting status, adding comments or otherwise indicating progress.
  </p>

  <a name="referral"> </a>
  <h4>Referral Management</h4>
  <p>
    As discussed on the <a href="interventions.html#referrals">interventions page</a>, referrals are the mechanism by which a Care Manager authorizes
    interventions to be performed by a physical activity professional.  The <a href="StructureDefinition-pa-servicerequest.html">referral record</a>
    is created and maintained exclusively on the Care Manager system.  However, Referral Recipient and Patient Engagement systems will have query access
    to the record.
  </p>
  <p>
    The <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.sdoh}}/StructureDefinition-SDOHCC-TaskForReferralManagement.html">Task</a> is what really drives the workflow.  
    Typically referrals won't be directed to a particular service provider.  Instead, Tasks will be used to solicit providers who are willing to
    perform a needed intervention (possibly with guidance from the patient around their preferences).  Referral Recipients will 
    <a href="#monitor">monitor</a> for new 'requested' Tasks assigned to them and will update the Tasks to indicate acceptance and, then 'in-progress',
    and eventually link the performed <a href="StructureDefinition-PA-Procedure.html">procedure</a> records to the Task and update the status to 'completed'.
  </p>
  <p>
    However, in addition to this 'happy' path, the Task is also used to document other workflows.  These include:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Changing the Task.status to 'rejected' and populating Task.reason.  E.g. the service provider is not accepting new patients.</li>  
    <li>After initially 'accepting' the task, changing the Task.status to 'cancelled' and populating Task.reason.  E.g. the service provider has become
      unavailable and is no longer able to satisfy the referral.</li>  
    <li>Changing the Task.status to 'on-hold' and populating Task.reason.  E.g. the patient has been hospitalized or gone on vacation.</li>  
    <li>Changing the Task.status to 'failed' and populating the Task.reason.  E.g. the patient has chosen to discontinue the training program.</li>
    <li>Changing the Task.businesStatus to communicate some degree of internal progress.  E.g. "completed intake session", "Developed workout plan",
      "'fading out' supports", etc.  (There is no requirement to do this, but it helps ensure everyone is on the same page.)</li>
    <li>Adding Task.note repetitions capturing progress against the Task.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    Alternatively, that Task might be updated by the Care Manager to cancel or fail the Task if the provider (usually in consultation with the patient)
    has determined that the referral is no longer appropriate/necessary.
  </p>
  <p>
    There are two different modes of operation for task management.  In one, the Task lives on the Care Manager system and is either
    polled or subscribed to by the Referral Recipient to monitor for initial creation and any Care Manager-side updates.  (The Gravity SDOHCC
    guide describes the differences between these two options in more detail <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.sdoh}}/checking_task_status.html">here</a>.)
    The Referral Recipient submits updates to the Care Manager to drive all record changes.  This approach means that the
    Referral Recipient doesn't need to expose a FHIR server interface and doesn't even need to have an ability to store health data locally.
  </p>
  <p>
    In the second, the Task is posted by the Care Manager to the Referral Recipient's system.  All changes are made locally and it is the
    Care Manager that polls or subscribes to the Task to monitor it for changes.  If the Care Manager needs to cancel the Task, they do so
    by submitting an update to the Referral Recipient.  In this approach, the Referral Recipient must have a FHIR server endpoint and that
    endpoint must be known to all Care Managers that will be sending orders.
  </p>
  <p>
    Gravity has a third mode of operation where intermediary systems act as a shared point of contact between Care Managers and Referral Recipients.
    This IG does not currently support an 'intermediary' architecture as there is not (yet?) an obvious set of intermediary vendors who could
    take on such a role.
  </p>
  
  <a name="feedback"> </a>
  <h4>Capturing Feedback and patient engagement</h4>
  <p>
    Another area where this implementation guide borrows from Gravity SDOH is in the use of Questionnaires to solicit feedback from patients (and
    their caregivers) about satisfaction with a particular service provider.  Patient satisfaction with their providers is a key indicator of their
    long-term success in improving and sustaining their physical activity levels.  (TODO - do we have any evidence for this?).  Gravity also uses
    the same Task-based mechanism to prompt patients to contact particular service providers, to review documentation, or to perform other 
    ad-hoc actions.
  </p>
  <p>
    This IG leverages the same <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.sdoh}}/StructureDefinition-SDOHCC-TaskForPatient.html">SDOHCC Task for Patient</a>
    profile because the requirements are the same and there is nothing in the profile that makes it specific to social determinants of health.
    The providers the patient is asked to contact, the literature they're asked to review, and the types of feedback they're asked to provide
    may differ.  However, the interoperability mechanisms for requesting the actions and capturing and monitoring the responses will be the same.
  </p>
  <p>
    The workflow is also the same.  The Patient Engagement app monitors for Tasks assigned to that patient and retrieves them and displays them
    to the patient, then updates the Task with the information from the completed task.
  </p>
  
  <a name="monitor"> </a>
  <h3>Monitoring for change</h3>
  <p>
    This IG involves resources that reside and are updated on one system (typically the Care Manager) that are of interest to other systems
    (typically the Patient Engagement and Referral Receiver systems).  There are two architectural mechanisms that can be used for such monitoring:
    polling and subscription.  The SDOH IG provides considerable detail about how each of these mechanisms functions for tasks 
    <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.sdoh}}/checking_task_status.html">here</a>.  
  </p>
</div>
