<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R4/fhir-single.xsd">
  <a name="status"> </a>
  <h3>Task status</h3>
  <p>
    This profile supports a number of <code>Task.status</code> codes.  The <a href="workflow.html#taskstatus">referral fufillment task 
    status diagram</a> on the Workflow page describes the relationships between the states.  The table below provides additional
    detail on each state, as well as rules around its use.
  </p>
  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Status</th>
        <th>Initiator</th>
        <th>Task Reason?</th>
        <th>Meaning</th>
        <th>Rules</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th>draft</th>
        <td>Care Manager</td>
        <td>No</td>
        <td>This will rarely, if ever, appear.  It would be relevant if a provider system has begun the work of deciding who to route a
          referral to, but has not yet actually clicked 'send' to make the request.</td>
        <td><i>Service Providers</i> <b>SHALL</b> either filter out or ignore Tasks in this state.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th><b>requested</b></th>
        <td>Care Manager</td>
        <td>No</td>
        <td>Indicates that fulfillment is being requested and no response has yet been provided.</td>
        <td>This <b>SHALL</b> be the initial status of the Task when it is first released for consideration.  Once the Task has left this status, 
          it <b>SHOULD NOT</b> return to this status, though in cases
          of an erroneous transition, a quick return to this status might be appropriate.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th><b>accepted</b></th>
        <td>Service Provider</td>
        <td>No</td>
        <td>Indicates that the <i>Service Provider</i> has agreed to perform the actions described in the referral ServiceRequest.</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th><b>rejected</b></th>
        <td>Service Provider</td>
        <td>Yes</td>
        <td>Indicates that the <i>Service Provider</i> does NOT agree to perform the actions described in the referral ServiceRequest.
          It is possible that, based on the reason for the refusal, the underlying ServiceRequest might be revised (or a new one created) 
          and a new Task seeking fulfillment could be created for the same target <i>Service Provider</i>.</td>
        <td>This is a final state.  When in this state, a <i>Task.statusReason</i> <b>SHALL</b> be provided explaining the refusal.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>cancelled</th>
        <td>Care Manager</td>
        <td>Yes</td>
        <td>Indicates the request for fulfillment has been terminated.  This occurs when the authorization for the action has been
          revoked.  This should happen only in exceptional circumstances, for example if the patient's clinical status changes in a way that
          would make the ordered therapy inappropriate.  A cancelled Task means the <i>Service Provider</i> should cease their interventions
          as soon as possible, though this may not be instantaneous.  A <i>Care Manager</i> should always make sure the patient is aware
          when an existing referral is being cancelled.</td>
        <td>Cancelled is a terminal state.  If there is subsequently a decision to seek continuation of an existing ServiceRequest after
          the Task has been cancelled, a new Task will be needed - which would then be accepted or rejected as usual.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>in-progress</th>
        <td>Service Provider</td>
        <td>No</td>
        <td>Used to distinguish that the requested work has actually begun.  E.g. The patient has started attending classes, the patient
          has come to their first consultation, etc.  Not all systems will track this information.</td>
        <td></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>on-hold</th>
        <td>Service Provider</td>
        <td>Yes</td>
        <td>Indicates that work on the service(s) requested by the referral has been temporarily paused.  For example, the patient has gone
          on vacation, the patient has suffered an injury that requires a break from activity, etc.  Communicating this is generally only
          relevant when the pause will significantly impact when the service might have been expected to complete and/or will result in a
          noticable change to the ongoing observations being communicated to the <i>Care Manager</i> to allow them to monitor progress.</td>
        <td>'on-hold' is a temporary state.  If the <i>Service Provider</i> determines after putting the Task on-hold that it will not
          resume, then the Task SHALL be transitioned to 'failed'.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>failed</th>
        <td>Service Provider</td>
        <td>Yes</td>
        <td>Indicates that the action(s) requested by the referral were attempted but could not be successfully completed.  For example,
          the patient stopped attending a program, the exercise professional determined their services were not a good match for the
          patient's needs, etc.</td>
        <td>Failed is a terminal state.  In order to solicit further action (from the same <i>Service Provider</i> or someone else, a new
          Task is needed, which will go through the Accept/Reject proecess the same as any other.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th><b>completed</b></th>
        <td>Service Provider</td>
        <td>No</td>
        <td>Indicates that the <i>Service Provider</i> believes they have completed all of the requested actions asked for as part of the
          <a href="StructureDefinition-pa-servicerequest.html">ServiceRequest</a>.  No further action is expected to be taken as part of
          the referral, though the <i>Service Provider</i> and the patient might still have further interaction through their own
          volition.</td>
        <td>It is up to the <i>Care Manager</i> to decide whether to update the ServiceRequest to 'completed'.  However, if further action
          is desired, a new Task will need to be initiated.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>entered-in-error</th>
        <td>Care Manager</td>
        <td>No</td>
        <td>Indicates that the Task record should never have existed.  E.g. A record was accidentally created against the wrong patient,
          against an unapproved order, against a completed order, etc.</td>
        <td><i>Service Providers</i> SHALL NOT filter out 'entered-in-error' Tasks so that they can see if a Task they've previously received
          gets marked as 'entered-in-error'.  If this occurs, then they SHOULD cease service as soon as possible and, if they opt to continue
          service, understand that it is not considered to be 'authorized' and may therefore have limitations with respect to insurance
          coverage.  In all other circumstances, <i>Service Providers</i> SHALL otherwise ignore 'entered-in-error' Tasks.</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <p>General Notes:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>When reading Task resources from another system, all statuses must be supported.  However, when updating Task status,
      <a href="CapabilityStatement-pa-service-provider.html">Service Providers</a> only need to be able to support those marked in bold.
      The remaining codes only need to be used when they are appropriate for the <i>Service Provider's</i> architecture.</li>
  </ul>
</div>